Let’s start this lecture with some motivation
In our previous lecture about multithreaded
processes, we saw that functions like pthread_join
exist to help users coordinate the execution
of threads that operate on shared memory.
In this lecture, we will discuss synchronization
in more detail.
Let’s start with an example.
Let’s assume we have 2 threads, A and B.
Each has a local variable x and a shared variable
S. That is, A and B share the same S variable.
S is initialized with value 20.
Let’s also assume A and B run in parallel,
each on its core.
Their code includes three instructions to
update S.
Let’s look at the example.
Each line represents an execution slot over
time.
We see that both A and B try to update S:
A by adding 50 while B by subtracting 20.
In this example, A starts one slot before
B. What is the problem with this execution?
Since the access to S is not synchronized
between A and B, A writes its update to S
after B has read the previous value of S.
Hence, rather than 20 + 50 - 20, the final
value of S is in fact 20 - 20.
If S represents your bank account balance,
you see such behavior is extremely risky.
As we will elaborate next, what we are experiencing
here is a race condition because of a critical
section that is not accessed exclusively.